So today we pick up on דף כ"ו עמוד ב' Daf Chaf
Vav Amud Bet at the very top. We discussed yesterday the issue
about making up a missed דאווענינג davening and the גמרא Gemara spoke,
said that it was possible even on a different day because although
there's a קרבן korban aspect of תפילות, tefillot, they were also רחמי
rachamei which is like a, you know, pouring out of our feelings
to God, a request for God's compassion, but basically it's a basic
human experience that transcends issues about time and text and so on.
And that is the ongoing sort of שאלה shailah with דאווענינג davening
because if it was really just רחמי rachamei there wouldn't be an
issue of having missed the time or having made up a time.
It would just be you דאוון daven when you want. So it
certainly is true that at the rabbinic level there's a fixed time
and text, but the idea that at its core it's רחמי rachamei
allows for the idea of, you know, of making it up and
about and doing things that are not always limited to the sort
of formal, rigid structure that we normally find by other מצוות. mitzvot.
We're going to continue with that today as we continue on the
top of דף כ"ו עמוד ב'. Daf Chaf Vav Amud Bet. Let's
take a look.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: so our rabbis taught, טעה ולא התפלל מנחה
בערב שבת מתפלל בלילי שבת שתים. Ta'ah velo hitpalel Mincha b'Erev Shabbat
mitpalel b'leilei Shabbat shtayim. So the same type of an idea, although
now we're talking about an issue which is what happens when the
תפילה tefillah changes, when you're in a different time zone as it
were, different... so you forgot to דאוון daven מנחה Mincha on Friday
and now it's שבת. Shabbat. You're going to do a makeup but
the makeup is going to mention שבת. Shabbat. The one you missed
was a Friday. So it says nevertheless you דאוון daven two on
שבת. Shabbat. טעה ולא התפלל מנחה בשבת מתפלל במוצאי שבת שתים של
חול.
Ta'ah velo hitpalel Mincha beShabbat mitpalel b'Motzei Shabbat shtayim
shel chol. Thanks. You make two on Saturday night and they're weekday
דאווענינגס davenings even though you are missing the שבת Shabbat דאווענינג. davening.
So the idea is that you've sort of abstracted it a little
bit and you say you miss a דאווענינג, davening, you make it
up at the next opportunity even though it lacks the character of
the דאווענינג davening that you missed. And now the גמרא's Gemara question
is the
following: מבדיל בראשונה ואינו מבדיל בשניה. Mavdil barishona v'eino mavdil bashniya. So
you make הבדלה Havdalah in the first one and now the גמרא
Gemara because yesterday it was a little ambiguous in the גמרא. Gemara.
Yesterday the גמרא Gemara made it sound a little bit like you
have a, you know, a second time to continue to דאוון. daven.
Now we're making it very clear that it's not like if you
missed מנחה Mincha time you can still דאוון daven it in the
next time, but that what you're doing in the next time is
you're doing a makeup. And because what you're doing, right, you understand
the conceptual difference? Okay. So since what you're doing is a makeup,
you first do your obligation and then you do your makeup.
One after the other? Yes, yes.
You
do one
and then right away another. How?
Can you explain to me the sense in that of
doing one after the other?
Just repetition just on a record twice?
Okay, okay. So at the, I guess that's an interesting point because
at the human experiential level, I guess it's fulfilling very little. Although
sometimes people דאוון daven and feel like, you know, I was really
not paying as much attention as I needed to. I really didn't
feel getting in touch with my feelings as I needed to. Like,
you know, sometimes I feel that way with the second סדר. Seder.
Everybody complains why is there a second סדר? Seder? I said, you
know, I didn't feel I did everything as much as as well
as I would have liked to the first סדר, Seder, so I
get a makeup. But I understand that that's not usually how people
feel and certainly not if it's immediately afterwards. And I think that
the answer is you're right, that it's not like we're trying to
do something to give you another sort of meaningful experience. For the
person who is praying, I assume it is not such a meaningful
experience that second time. What we're trying to do is basically check
off a requirement off of a list. You owed a דאווענינג, davening,
you missed a דאווענינג, davening, you're making it up. We're checking off
of a list. But you are right that it's ironic because if
the reason you're allowed to make it up is based on the,
is based on the sort of human experience of prayer, the religious
experience of prayer, but then the actual making of it up is
a very formalistic type of and not sort of experientially meaningful making
up. It's a very good question.
I see what you're bringing into it.
Yeah, that's also true. But what they're saying, it's hard, it's not
impossible, but it's hard to bring in a meaningful second experience following
right after the first one. Right after the first? Yeah, well that's
what we do. Yeah, fine. A one minute break or whatever. That's
true. But you know, but still the question is a good question.
Yes, and who do you owe it to?
Well, who do you owe anything to? I mean if you're supposed
to do a מצווה, mitzvah, you're supposed to do an obligation. I
mean, you know, it's our sense of חיוב chiyuv and מצוות mitzvot
and so on of doing our life as Jews, of our religious
obligation.
עבר זמנו בטל קרבנו. Avar zmano batel korbano.
Well, okay. But I hear your point. Your point is a good
one, which is that if what's allowing you to do it is
the aspect of, of this is an inner religious experience, then how
much is that really being fulfilled if it's being done immediately afterwards?
It's a very good point.
I'd have to ask that question on the other extreme position we
heard, that הלוואי יתפלל אדם כל היום כולו. halevai yitpalel adam kol
hayom kulo.
Right, right.
But they had
made formal prayer.
Well no, that was used to, that was used to... Used to
allow דאווענען davening another שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei whenever you wanted. But
at least there it's different in the sense that there the question
here is that it's immediately afterwards, it's not coming through any sort
of inner type of motivation, of initiative. It's a good question. It's
a very good question.
It speaks to compulsiveness.
That I don't know, but it's a good question. It does speak
to what happens when you try to bring these two very different
things together: the profound universal human experience of prayer together with a
formalized external fixed text, fixed time, that is rabbinic prayer.
Is there no counter? In the sense of somebody else saying don't
make it up?
No, that seems to be the consensus of the גמרא. Gemara. So
let's, so I hear the question, let's keep on going. So גמרא
Gemara says like this: Now, you make up on the first one
because the first one is your obligation, and here we're very clearly
structuring it as a makeup. So after you do your first one,
אין המבדיל בשניה, ein hamavdil bishniya, don't make הבדלה havdalah on the
second. ואם
הבדיל בשניה, v'im hivdil bishniya, if you made הבדלה havdalah on the
second, ולא הבדיל בראשונה, v'lo hivdil bishona, and not on the first,
so by doing that you have basically designated the first one to
be your makeup and your second one to be your official מעריב.
Ma'ariv. And if that's what you've designated it as, so שניה עלתה
לו ראשונה לא עלתה לו. shniya alta lo rishona lo alta lo.
So only the second one counts, the second because you have to
דאווענען daven your obligation first. That's the way חז"ל Chazal have formalized
this idea of makeup. And therefore your first one, which was by
your actions you were showing that it was not your מעריב, Ma'ariv,
but it was your makeup, that didn't count. The makeup only counts
after the first. So
גמרא Gemara says, למימרא דכיון דלא עבד בקמייתא כמאן דלא צלי דמי?
l'memra d'keivan d'lo avdei b'kamaisa k'man d'lo tzalya dami? So the גמרא
Gemara isn't willing to say it's all about this new idea of
makeup. It wants to think that maybe what you're suggesting is that
since you didn't make הבדלה havdalah in the first דאווענען davening it
didn't count? That מעריב Ma'ariv without הבדלה havdalah מוצאי שבת motzaei Shabbos
doesn't count? Is that what you're saying? ומהדרינן ליה? u'mahadruna lei? We
make you go back? רמינהו? reminaihu? I'll show you that's not true.
Even if you missed הבדלה havdalah during מעריב, Ma'ariv, it counts, it
counts. תנא לא הזכיר גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים, Tana: lo hizkir gvurot
geshamim bit'chiat hameitim, if somebody forgot to mention משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
mashiv haruach umorid hagashem in the second ברכה, bracha, גבורות גשמים, gvurot
geshamim, the power of the rain that we see today, ושאלה בברכת
השנים v'sha'alah b'virchat hashanim or ותן טל ומטר לברכה v'ten tal u'matar
livracha in the ברכה bracha of the years, of sustenance, מחזירין אותו,
mahzirin oto, you make him go back. Those are things that have
to be corrected. הבדלה בחונן הדעת, havdalah b'honen hada'at, if somebody left
off doing the המבדיל hamavdil in the first ברכה bracha after the
three, the ברכה bracha of חונן הדעת, Honen Hada'at, אין מחזירין אותו,
ein mahzirin oto, you don't make him go back, מפני שיכול לאומרה
על הכוס, mipnei sheyachol l'omra al hakos, he'll say הבדלה havdalah later
on a cup of wine. So how come the first one didn't
count? It should be a מעריב Ma'ariv anyway, even if you missed
your הבדלה havdalah it still counts. So גמרא Gemara says, קשיא, kashya,
difficult. But it's not really so difficult, because as רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot both point out, if all you were doing was דאווענען
davening מעריב Ma'ariv and you missed הבדלה, havdalah, you would be יוצא.
yotzei. But here we are setting up a requirement that in order
to do a makeup, it has to be defined as first your
obligatory, then your makeup, and through where you set הבדלה, havdalah, you
have labeled them incorrectly, so only the second one counts as the
obligatory, the first one does not count. And it goes back to
the point that Rivka and Rachel were saying, that becomes very fascinating
how something that is allowed because it's not all about structure and
laws and formal
definitions, it's allowed because of the human experience of prayer is now
becoming highly structured, so that even if you did two דאווענען davenings
it won't necessarily count unless clearly one has been labeled the obligation
and the other labeled the makeup. Yes.
So this is according to the opinion that מעריב Ma'ariv is a
חיוב. chiyuv. Yes. And if מעריב Ma'ariv is a רשות? reshut?
So that's a good question. We're going to get to that later.
תוספות Tosafot pointed that out before and תוספות Tosafot said that all
these discussions about making up, well this is making up מנחה, Mincha,
but anyway, the discussion earlier about making up מעריב Ma'ariv assumes it's
an obligation, that'll be debated later. So let's just note that for
now, here it does feel you have to do מעריב Ma'ariv and
you have to make it up. We'll get back to it later.
Yes.
Two things, an interesting thing is also that these days, even let's
say you wanted to take the opposite way and saying I really
feel so, whatever it is, I feel like I'm having such a
great כוונה kavana and I want to do another תפילה tefilla in
נדבה, nedaba, we discourage that these days, don't we? So even from
the personal הלואי שיתפלל אדם כל היום כולו, halevai sheyitpallel adam kol
hayom kulo, we don't really say that anymore.
Well, we apply it in very small ways, but you're correct, meaning
what Michael is saying is correct and it reinforces the point that
was made before, which is
that we're dealing within the halakhic system, so it's not going to
come as a surprise that the
formal halakhic approach is going to dominate, and is going to
really be the one that even within this interesting phenomenon of תפילה,
tefilla, it's going to much more tip towards the formalist type of
idea. So you're right, even though we allow the רחמי rachamei for
a certain amount of latitude, we don't go ahead and say just
go ahead and דאווענען daven any time you want, just go ahead
and like add randomly to the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, the formal
rules, we are talking about הלכה, halakha, so the formal rules are
going to be really much more dominant, and it reinforces the point
before that even though this is allowed because of רחמי. rachamei. It
expresses itself in very sort of external, formal ways. I'll give you
one simple example that even is not about just doing another שמונה
עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. I'm, you know, if you ask a—שאלות shailos were
asked of various פוסקים, poskim, if I feel I can have more
כוונה kavana at home, should I דאווען daven at home or should
I דאווען daven in שול? shul? And overwhelmingly the פוסקים poskim say
דאווען daven in שול. shul. Right? They—we are going to favor the
formal fulfillment of prayer over the internal, you know, כוונה kavana internal
experience. Now there are some that disagree, okay, but overwhelmingly that is
not as a surprise in a halachic system that that's the way
it's going to tip. But at least what I find is interesting
is this is the one place where at least you have a
very clear dialectic about that. You know, you have that very clear
tension, you usually don't even have that tension.
Well and I think a good reason for that is imagine the
50 men decided on the same day that their כוונה kavana would
be better at home and nobody's in שול.
shul. Yeah, you know what? I think they'd say the same, I
think they'd say the same answer for a woman asked the question.
So I don't think it was just to ensure that there was
a מנין. minyan. But you're just saying the numbers, the numbers.
Point is as a rabbi in this case no מנין minyan because
everybody's at home.
Right, and that is a good point too and we'll get to
that as well. That in addition to the sense of sort of
formal external obligation, inner experience, is also the question about personal versus
communal prayer and the nature of prayer as a communal experience and
that's another point as well. Charlie?
Well much of the Jewish world does not think that women should
go to שול. shul.
Okay, we're not getting there. Charlie.
So when you דאווען daven your מנחה mincha twice do you do
the second שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei before or after עלינו? Aleinu?
I don't, I do it אשרי Ashrei before—אשרי Ashrei before עלינו Aleinu
because עלינו Aleinu is a bit too much of a break. But
anyway we'll talk about that afterwards offline. Anyway let's go on. So
now, so that's the הלכה. halacha. I'll tell you, I need to
tell you one very important question that תוספות Tosafot asks about this,
a practical question which is that תוספות Tosafot says let's say the
reason you—you didn't really miss a שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. You said
the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei but you missed a critical part like,
yeah, it was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and you missed יעלה ויבא.
Ya'aleh V'Yavo. And now it's מנחה. mincha. And now it's מעריב. maariv.
Do you do a makeup? So תוספות Tosafot has two opinions. On
the one hand do a makeup, you weren't יוצא yotzei מנחה. mincha.
On the other hand if you're going to do a makeup it's
מעריב, maariv, you're not going to say יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh V'Yavo anyway
because it's no longer ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and you could, right?
So תוספות Tosafot what? So תוספות Tosafot differentiates from the גמרא. gemara.
The גמרא gemara you totally missed it. Here you said it without
this component and you won't be able to do the component afterwards
anyway. So the question to a large degree is what do we
think it means to have דאווען davened let's say שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei without יעלה ויבא? Ya'aleh V'Yavo? Does it mean that you basically
didn't fulfill your obligation of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei or does it
mean you fulfilled the obligation of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei but you
didn't fulfill the obligation to say יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh V'Yavo in שמונה
עשרה? Shmoneh Esrei? So if it's you don't just, weren't יוצא yotzei
יעלה ויבא, Ya'aleh V'Yavo, why do it again? You're also not going
to be יוצא yotzei יעלה ויבא. Ya'aleh V'Yavo. But if it's that
you were not יוצא yotzei שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, okay, so it's
just the same as if you hadn't דאווען. davened. So you do
it again at night even though it will no longer be ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Like the גמרא gemara you did it at night
even though it's no longer שבת. Shabbat. And that's the way that
we פסקן. pasken. We פסקן pasken if you miss like a יעלה
ויבא Ya'aleh V'Yavo in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei you דאווען daven מוצא—you
motzo דאווען daven a second one at
מעריב maariv even though you're not going to say יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh
V'Yavo and similar by analogous types of issues. It's considered like you
weren't יוצא yotzei the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, not you missed doing
the thing. We focus on not being יוצא yotzei the שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei and you do a makeup. Yes.
I want to try to formulate the question better because when you
say you're not יוצא yotzei what does it mean? God didn't listen
to it?
No, so again that's the same point, you know. You could, you
could, I don't know, I don't understand, it's not silly, it's only
silly because you are so much in the רחמי rachme mode that
you can't think about תפילה tefila as a formal obligation. Let's say
I spent Wednesday thinking about God as creator of the world and
focusing on God having rested after creation and the יציאת מצרים Yetziat
Mitzrayim and all of that. What do you mean I wasn't יוצא
yotzei שבת? Shabbat? You know, I spent the whole day thinking about
the right things.
You make קידוש. Kiddush.
What? Let's say I made קידוש Kiddush on a Wednesday. What do
you mean I wasn't יוצא yotzei שבת? Shabbat? Okay.
So the point is that by all other things you take it
for granted that there's an idea of doing your obligations defined by
certain formal, you know, criteria and you know, and very, very quantifiable
ways. But by prayer you basically are seeing prayer only in the
רחמי rachme mode. All prayer is is me talking to God, all
this other stuff shouldn't matter. But the rabbis created an obligation of
prayer with fixed text and fixed time and stuff. So yes, we've
got to move on.
This is the thing that makes us different from the Reform.
Okay, there you go. Alright, moving on. Now the גמרא gemara says
like this.
Okay, I just have to tell you, I know we're sort of
postponing but one more thing about this because there's a great story
with רב Rav חיים—רב חיים from בריסק—which Brisk is, which is,
it actually comes up. Let's say somebody forgot to דאווען daven מעריב
maariv on מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbat. So now they're דאווענינג davening שחרית,
Shacharit, they do a double שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Which one do
they say יעלה ויבא—which Ya'aleh V'Yavo one do they say אתה חוננתנו?
Atah Chonantanu? No, so you would think based on this you say
it in the second because the second is the makeup, so you
say אתה חוננתנו. Atah Chonantanu. So he said follow the פוסקים—no, poskim
but even if you say... even if you do הבדלה על הכוס
Havdalah Al Ha-Kos before you דאוון daven מעריב, Maariv, you still do
המבדיל Ha-Mavdil in מעריב. Maariv.
You don't say יעלה ויבוא?
Yaaleh Ve-Yavo? No, forget יעלה ויבוא. Yaaleh Ve-Yavo. I'm saying you missed,
you missed מעריב מוצאי שבת. Maariv Motzaei Shabbos You didn't say, so
now you have to דאוון daven a double שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
שחרית. Shacharis. So one of them counts for the מוצאי שבת Motzaei
Shabbos. מעריב, Maariv the second one presumably. You would say המבדיל Ha-Mavdil
in the second one. That's what the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah rules.
So the פרחי Pirchei says no, you say המבדיל Ha-Mavdil in the
first one. Why? Because it says המבדיל Ha-Mavdil is not a הלכה
halachah of מעריב Maariv, מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbos to say המבדיל. Ha-Mavdil.
המבדיל Ha-Mavdil is a הלכה halachah that the first שמנה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei you דאוון daven after שבת, Shabbos, you say המבדיל Ha-Mavdil in.
So here it happened to be the first שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
was שחרית. Shacharis. So anyway, it's in the first one. What? Yeah,
well that's true, even if you do הבדלה על הכוס Havdalah Al
Ha-Kos you still do המבדיל Ha-Mavdil in מעריב. Maariv.
Okay, I'm not going to it any further, I shouldn't have even
said it. הגמרא, Ha-Gemara, let's go on. הגמרא Ha-Gemara says like this.
Okay, so it says like this.
איתמר. Itmar. רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא אמר. Rabbi Yose Berabbi Chanina Amar. Now okay, now we get
to the whole to the whole
real core issue. I think this spells very nicely in this following
גמרא. Gemara. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose Berabbi Chanina says תפילות
אבות תיקנום. Tefilos Avos Tiknum. The תפילות tefilos were established by the
forefathers, אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak Ve-Yaakov. רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר
תפילות כנגד תמידים תיקנום. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi Omer Tefilos Keneged Temidim
Tiknum. The תפילות tefilos were established to correspond to the daily sacrifices.
Now what does that, well let's just read a little bit more.
תניא כוותיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא ותניא כוותיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי.
Tanya Kevasei De-Rabbi Yose Berabbi Chanina Ve-Tanya Kevasei De-Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi.
We taught a ברייתא braisa supporting each one. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא Tanya Kevasei De-Rabbi Yose Berabbi Chanina that it was about
the fathers, the forefathers. אברהם תיקן תפילת שחרית. Avraham Tiken Tefilas Shacharis.
אברהם Avraham established שחרית, Shacharis, שנאמר וישכם אברהם בבוקר אל המקום אשר
עמד שם. Shene'emar Vayashkem Avraham Baboker El Hamakom Asher Amad Sham. אברהם
Avraham rose up early in the morning to the place where he
had stood and that obviously was preceding praying for סדום ועמורה, Sedom
Va-Amorah, so in that case preceding a whole experience of prayer.
ואין עמידה אלא תפילה Ve'ein Amidah Ela Tefilah and to stand means
to pray, שנאמר ויעמוד פנחס ויפלל. Shene'emar Vaya'amod Pinchas Vayefalel. פנחס Pinchas
stood and here יפלל Yefalel is reading יתפלל Yispallel prayed, could mean
he judged, but anyway here it's reading prayer. So stand means to
pray.
And he did it when? He did וישכם, Vayashkem, he did it
in the morning. יצחק תיקן תפילת מנחה. Yitzchak Tiken Tefilas Minchah. יצחק
Yitzchak established מנחה, Minchah, שנאמר ויצא יצחק לשוח בשדה לפנות ערב. Shene'emar
Vayetze Yitzchak Lasuach Basadeh Lifnos Arev.
יצחק Yitzchak went out to speak in the field, meditate in the
field towards evening time. So towards evening time means it's not yet
night and it's still like midday or like late afternoon, so that's
מנחה. Minchah. ואין שיחה אלא תפילה Ve'ein Sichah Ela Tefilah and speech
means prayer, שנאמר תפילה לעני כי יעטוף ולפני השם ישפוך שיחו, Shene'emar
Tefilah Le'ani Ki Ya'atof Velifne Hashem Yishpoch Sicho, a prayer for a
poor person who faints or who wraps himself and before השם Hashem
pours out his speech. יעקב תיקן תפילת ערבית. Yaakov Tiken Tefilas Arvis.
יעקב Yaakov established מעריב, Maariv, ערבית, Arvis, שנאמר ויפגע במקום וילן שם.
Shene'emar Vayifga Bamakhom Vayalen Sham. And there he encountered the place and
he and he slept there. Now there you don't actually hear him
praying, I mean he prays when he wakes up the next morning,
but nevertheless we are reading it as, and that's night obviously he
goes to sleep. ואין פגיעה אלא תפילה. Ve'ein Pegiah Ela Tefilah. To
be פוגע, pogea, to encounter, I'll be I'll say that in a
minute, means prayer, שנאמר ואתה אל תתפלל בעד העם הזה ואל תשא
בעדם רינה ותפילה ואל תפגע בי. Shene'emar Ve'atah Al Tispallel Bead Ha'am
Hazeh Ve'al Tisa Ba'adam Rinah Utefilah Ve'al Tifga Bi. Do not pray
for the sake of this nation and do not lift up for
them song and prayer and do not encounter me now, probably a
better translation or context here doesn't just mean encounter, right, but it
means to importune. Do not like, you know, sort of try to
try to entreat me, entreat and importune me exactly. So that is
three models of prayer, שחרית מנחה ומעריב. Shacharis Minchah U-Maariv. Just hold
off some questions for a minute, let's read a little bit and
then I want to get back, I have some things I want
to say. ותניא כוותיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי. Ve-Tanya Kevasei De-Rabbi Yehoshua
Ben Levi. We taught like רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. מפני מה אמרו תפילת השחר עד חצות? Mipnei Mah Ameru Tefilas
Hashachar Ad Chatzos? Why did we say that the morning prayer goes
only until midday? שהרי תמיד של שחר קרב והולך עד חצות, Sheharei
Tamid Shel Shachar Karev Ve-holech Ad Chatzos, because it's based on the
model of the communal daily sacrifices until midday. רבי יהודה אומר עד
ארבע שעות, Rabbi Yehudah Omer Ad Arba Shaos, only until four hours,
שהרי תמיד של שחר קרב והולך עד ארבע שעות. Sheharei Tamid Shel
Shachar Karev Ve-holech Ad Arba Shaos. He thinks the communal morning sacrifice,
the תמיד, tamid, only goes until four hours into the day, until
10:00. Apparently and presumably they never did it past 10, but the
question was הלכתית halachically would it be possible until until noon. ומפני
מה אמרו תפילת המנחה עד הערב? Umipnei Mah Ameru Tefilas Ha-Minchah Ad
Ha-erev? Why is the מנחה Minchah prayer until night? שהרי תמיד של
בין הערביים קרב והולך עד הערב, Sheharei Tamid Shel Bein Ha-arbayim Karev
Ve-holech Ad Ha-erev, because the afternoon תמיד tamid communal sacrifice could go
until nightfall. רבי יהודה אומר עד פלג המנחה. Rabbi Yehudah Omer Ad
Pelag Ha-minchah. No, you can only do it until the פלג המנחה,
Pelag Ha-minchah, half of the מנחה, Minchah, which means basically till an
hour and a quarter before sunset, שהרי תמיד של בין הערביים קרב
והולך עד פלג המנחה. Sheharei Tamid Shel Bein Ha-arbayim Karev Ve-holech Ad
Pelag Ha-minchah. That's only how long you could bring the communal sacrifice,
not all the way until sunset. ומפני מה אמרו תפילת הערב אין
לה קבע? Umipnei Mah Ameru Tefilas Ha-erev Ein Lah Keva? Why does
nighttime prayer have no limit? שהרי איברים ופדרים שלא נתעכלו מבערב קרבים
והולכים כל הלילה. Sheharei Eivarim U-fedarim Shelo Nitalu Mi-ba'erev Karevim Ve-holchim Kol
Ha-laylah. The fats and the limbs of the sacrifices that were not
consumed by the fire from before
nightfall could be burned the entire night. Okay. ומפני מה אמרו Umipnei
Mah Ameru and the last one is של מוספים כל היום. Shel
Musafim Kol Hayom. You can דאוון daven מוסף Musaf all day, שהרי
קורבן של מוספים קרב כל היום, Sheharei Korban Shel Musafim Karev Kol
Hayom, because the מוסף Musaf could be done the whole day and
therefore you could say מוסף Musaf the whole day. רבי יהודה אומר
עד שבע שעות. Rabbi Yehudah Omer Ad Sheva Shaos. No, only until
seven hours into the day, 1:00 PM, שהרי קורבן מוסף קרב והולך
עד שבע שעות, Sheharei Korban Musaf Karev Ve-holech Ad Sheva Shaos, because
קורבן מוסף Korban Musaf can only be brought until 1:00 PM. Okay,
I guess let's just finish this whole ברייתא braisa and then we'll
go back and discuss. ואיזו היא מנחה? Ve'eizo Hi Minchah? ואיזו היא
מנחה גדולה Mincha Gedola, *Ve'eizo hi Mincha gedolah* what is the big
מנחה Mincha, *Mincha* meaning the larger time of מנחה Mincha *Mincha* as
early as מנחה Mincha, *Mincha* could be told משש שעות ומחצה ולמעלה
*mishesh sha'ot umachetza ule'ma'lah* from six and a half hours onward 12:30
PM onward already you can start מנחה Mincha. *Mincha* and that gives
you a whole five and a half hours to דאבן *daven* מנחה
Mincha *Mincha*. ואיזו היא מנחה קטנה Mincha Ketana *Ve'eizo hi Mincha ketanah*
what is the smaller מנחה Mincha *Mincha* which is the more ideal
time to דאבן *daven* מנחה Mincha *Mincha* because it more corresponded to
when the afternoon sacrifice was brought? מתשע שעות ומחצה ולמעלה *Mitesha sha'ot
umachetza ule'ma'lah* from nine and a half hours 3:30 until the end.
And that now let's just stop there for a minute. So
here you have the two
models כנגד אבות kineged avot *keneged Avot* and כנגד קרבנות kineged korbanot.
*keneged Korbanot*. כנגד kineged? קרבנות Korbanot.
*Keneged Korbanot* is very clear it corresponds to when the sacrifices were
brought. It's very specific times based on those times there's some debate
of those times but that's what it's based on. Okay the אבות
Avot. *Avot* is the we see the אבות avot, *Avot* prayed and
maybe it's a little bit of a stretch here and there like
by יצחק Yitzchak, *Yitzchak* or by יעקב Yaakov: *Yaakov* but the idea
that they prayed at different times during the day. Now some people
read this גמרא Gemara? *Gemara* as a historical question right? Who were
the people or when were the תפילות Tfillot *tefillot* established? There's obviously
a big problem with reading it as a historical question because the
two answers are not addressing the same question right? The first answer
says אבות Avot, *Avot* that gives you a when and a who.
The second answer says it corresponds to the קרבנות Korbanot *Korbanot*. Okay
when was it done? Who did it? Doesn't tell you either right?
You look in רש"י *Rashi* רש"י *Rashi* says אנשי כנסת הגדולה *Anshei
Knesset HaGedolah*. Some people assume if it says קרבנות Korbanot. *Korbanot* it
means post the destruction of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* because then
they needed something to correspond to קרבנות Korbanot *Korbanot*. But רש"י *Rashi*
says אנשי כנסת הגדולה *Anshei Knesset HaGedolah* which was already when there
was a second בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. So it doesn't answer the
same question if it's a historical question about who or when. And
it seems very clearly it's not a question of who or when
but a question of the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* phrases the
question is כנגד kineged. מי *keneged mi* corresponding to what which means
what is the model of תפילה Tefilla *tefillah*? And this גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* I think is very clearly sort of laying out what otherwise
was called קרבן Korban *korban* versus רחמי *rachamei*. Here it's קרבן Korban
*korban* versus אבות Avot *Avot*. Is the model the אבות *Avot* which
is the model that is being sort of pushed over here on
this side of the table which is what was the אבות *Avot*'s
experience of prayer? Their experience was not like if you take this
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* literally so every morning אברהם Avraham, *Avraham* got up
at 10:00 to דאבן שחרית Shacharit, *daven Shacharit*. Then every day מנחה
Mincha *Mincha* at time to דאבן שחרית Shacharit, *daven Shacharit* time to
דאבן מנחה Mincha *daven Mincha*. By the time of יעקב Yaakov, *Yaakov*
they דאבן *daven* from 11:00, 2:00, 8:00, 12:00, just say obviously that
is completely in contradiction to what we read in the תורה *Torah*.
What we read in the תורה *Torah* is profound prayer of the
אבות *Avot* but it was a very innerly
compelled inner human experience of prayer spontaneous prayer coming from the heart
no fixed text no fixed time responding to needs and circumstances. That
was the prayer of the אבות *Avot*. That's one model of prayer.
That is in strong contrast sharp contrast to the קרבנות Korbanot. *Korbanot*
which is all about fixed times. What's קרבנות Korbanot. *Korbanot* right? When
we get up to ויקרא *Vayikra* in the תורה *Torah* it's like
enormous million little details and rituals. That's the קרבנות Korbanot. *Korbanot*. Every
detail specific text specific way specific time. How do you do it?
How do you stand? Where do you stand? All of those details
that is תפילה Tefilla כנגד קרבנות Korbanot. *tefillah keneged Korbanot* and these
are the two competing models. Is it the inner experience? Is it
the I in a שיעור *shiur* I give on this one sometimes
I call it prayer from the heart or prayer from the סידור
*siddur* right? You have these two different models and they're very different.
One is you ask are you יוצא *yotze* which Rachel takes offense
at. Are you יוצא *yotze*? You spoke to God. Okay those are
the two different ways of looking at prayer. Now I want to
say now how do they resolve? We'll see in a minute how
it resolves itself but even before we get to that I want
to say two things one or two more things. First of all
if it is אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak VeYaakov. *Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov*
are seen as the model and it's the human experience then well
I want to say well let me take a step back before
I say that. First of all the three verbs that the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* uses to stand right אברהם Avraham? *Avraham* stands יצחק Yitzchak.
*Yitzchak* speaks and יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* entreats. So this is what I'm
sharing is not mine I don't remember where I heard this but
I think it was from the רב Rav *Rav* but it might
have been from elsewhere. That that also speaks to three aspects about
what the prayer experience is about. The very first part of the
prayer experience is even before you say anything. Standing before God. According
to the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* the basic כוונה *kavanah* needed for prayer
even before you get to understanding the words you're saying is the
awareness that you're in the presence of God. And just being aware
that you're in the presence of God I mean that in itself
is a form a profound form of connection right? Being consciously in
the presence of another is a even without speech to me the
most profound form of connecting. That's the first move of prayer. Then
you take the next step and you actually sort of articulate your
thoughts and narrow them and articulate them into speech and that's the
next move of יצחק Yitzchak *Yitzchak* which is שיחה *sichah*. And only
after that that you have the connection and you have the connection
verbalized in speech then we get to the aspect of prayer which
is פגיעה *pegiah* which is entreating which is בקשה *bakasha*. So sometimes
prayer is seen as primarily בקשה *bakasha* requesting but the primary prayer
experience every prayer experience sort of transcends receives
the three stages by fundamentally creating the sense of connection: non-verbal connection,
verbal connection, and then finally entreating which is יעקב. So that's just,
I think, to appreciate in terms of the three verbs here's three
stages. The other thing to be point to be made, and this
is something is a teaching I heard from the הרב, Rav, which
is the idea of what do we mean אברהם, Avraham יצחק, Yitzchak
and יעקב: שחרית, Shacharit, מנחה, Mincha and מעריב, Maariv, if we're just
saying that it's not about fixed times.
And the answer given is that we're not talking about different times
to pray but different ways to pray. That you can have a
תפילה Tefilla which is a morning prayer, whenever you're praying it. And
a תפילה Tefilla that's an afternoon prayer, and it's not when you're
praying but it's what type of a prayer it is. The morning
prayer is, right, what is the experience of morning? Right, the experience
of morning is most people, usually after your first cup of coffee,
whatever, you wake up and you're filled with life and hope and
a sense of possibility, you know, a new day is dawning. It's
a prayer of dreams, of ambitions, of visions, of accomplishing things in
the world. Who was אברהם? Avraham. Right, אברהם Avraham. was the pioneer.
He went out and he spread God's words throughout the world everywhere
he went. ויקרא בשם ה׳. Vayikra Beshem Hashem. He was out to
conquer world. Right, he was and he literally, you know, he was
bringing people to serve God, fighting wars. This is the dream of
ambition and visions and, you know, and accomplishment. That's one type of
prayer we make. Then you get to יצחק. Yitzchak, יצחק Yitzchak did
not have too many of his own visions and dreams and whatever.
יצחק Yitzchak. was primarily the continuity of אברהם. Avraham Right, primarily a
set... All right, you know what, this is my דבר תורה. Dvar
Torah. You can say...
I'm getting so upset.
So what we see primarily about יצחק, Yitzchak. what we see primarily
about יצחק Yitzchak... is that is there is nothing, and to the
degree that he did something he continued אברהם. Avraham. He says he
dug the same wells that אברהם Avraham, dug, you know, he had
the same story with his wife and with whatever, אבימלך. Avimelech. He
was very much a continuity of אברהם. Avraham. And the reason is
because after an אברהם, Avraham, you don't need another אברהם. Avraham, Right,
after an אברהם, Avraham if everybody's an אברהם, Avraham then the religion
doesn't get anywhere. You need somebody to come and to institutionalize it
and to lay roots and to lay foundation and to ensure its
continuity. Because אברהם's Avraham wells, all of אברהם's Avraham, חידושים, Chiddushim, all
of אברהם's accomplishments, you know, get stopped up if nobody is continuing
to maintain those wells and dig the wells and keep the water
flowing. And that's the life of יצחק. And the תפילה Tefilla of
מנחה Mincha is, you know, by the time you get to the
midday, most of your dreams of the morning are a little bit
okay we'll worry about that tomorrow. And what you need is your
second cup of coffee to get through the day and to keep
up your strength and continuity and to keep things on track and
to keep things going, pass it down to the next generation. Those
are the תפילות of יצחק. And the תפילה tefillah of יעקב, יעקב
was the person that was constantly beset by trouble. And he's running
away from עשו Esav and he's praying to God to save him,
you know, he's going to לבן Lavan and it's always עשו, Esav,
it's לבן, Lavan, it's יוסף. Yosef. Those are the prayers of night.
Those are the prayers of fear, of danger, of trouble, of anguish,
when you don't know what's coming and you're praying to God, right,
to help you for salvation. So that is an idea of setting
right there, you see? So that is the prayers of אברהם,
יצחק... That's a way of understanding these as not as times of
prayer but as types of prayer. Now, that is in stark contrast
to the fixed prayers of the קרבנות. Korbanot. Now, one thing to
note about that as well though is, there's another important part about
the fixed, because then you'd say oh that was so lovely why
do we need all the fixed external aspects of it? Well, one
answer reason is, which is that the first ex- that not everybody
is able to do the inner prayer and the fixed external aspects
gives people a text and gives them a regularity and waits for
the spirit to move you, you're never going to דאוון Daven so
hopefully you דאוון Daven on a regular basis and that you'll sometimes
be able to connect even if it's not all the time. But
there's another answer as well, which is that the fixed nature of
the, it's that the קרבן Korban that this corresponds to is which
קרבנות Korbanot, does the תפילה correspond to according to the גמרא? Gemara:
תמיד, Tamid, the communal sacrifice. Because what you give up in the
personal experience when you do all of the forms of prayer is
that you achieve a communal experience. Is that if we're all דאוונינג
Davening at the same time and we're all דאוונינג Davening the same
text, even if certainly if we're all דאוונינג Davening in the same
place and we have a מנין Minyan and we have a ציבור,
Tzibur, but even without that, prayer is now not just everybody's own
personal thoughts to God, right? We now become a community of prayer
that we have a shared prayer. So the formal aspects what they
give up in terms of the personal inner experience, they achieve something
in terms of that communal aspect of prayer which is represented by
the קרבנות. Korbanot, So that I think really is the two models
that are being presented here, and the ongoing question we deal with
in this מסכת Masechet is how to find, you know, how those
two continue to work together or in opposition.
Yes, every every form and human endeavor that unlocks meaning has this
tension. Otherwise you wouldn't write down music in... Any human endeavor
that contains the potential for inspiration and meaning is organized around this
tension between formal structure and the unlocking of kind of a moment
of inner meaning. Otherwise, for example, in music there would be no
formalized way to write the notes down and for me to try
to gain the discipline by learning how to play the music, if
it's only routine, mindless, it becomes boring. But the idea I thought
was that it unlocks the potential along the way, so to speak.
Theater has that too. Every endeavor has that tension at its heart.
Yeah, that's very beautiful. You know, when I sometimes talk about this,
I actually give that example and from I don't know if you
remember this movie, A Beautiful Mind? So there's a great theme there
where like the guy was no, wait, was that the movie? Or
maybe it was no, that was about the mathematician, right? I'm thinking
about a different movie
about some musician or someone. Anyway, that he had to do his
own
thing and his teacher was trying to teach him the rigors
of the discipline of music, of structure and so on. So he
said, basically said, first learn the structure and then you can forget
it. So you know, you first have to get the rigor and
then you can bring your own personal expression to it. Somebody once
gave me the example of like jazz, which has the sense of
improvisation within the structure and so on. So that will become a
question. How much of that personal allowing do we do for that
improvisation or for then forget the notes? After you've learned the notes,
then you can forget them. Yes.
There are
corners of the Christian world that aren't tiny that deny the validity
of fixed orders of prayer, insist that the only thing that matters
is spontaneity.
Okay, here you go. All right, so let's now continue in the
גמרא. Gemara So we have those two models. So now the גמרא
Gemara is going to be: okay, which one is right? So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says: איבעיא להו, Ibayya Lehu,
they raised the question. We're about eight lines down in the wide
lines toward the end of the line: רבי יהודה פלג מנחה קמא
קאמר או פלג מנחה אחרונה קאמר. Rabbi Yehuda Pelag Mincha Kama Ka'amar
O Pelag Mincha Achrona Ka'amar. So before we get to resolving this
tension, we have to figure out a detail. When he said to
half the מנחה, Mincha. right, which half did he say? The first
one or the second one? Meaning, if you take the whole six
hours of the afternoon, you divide it in two halves. So there's
the, you know, because he actually said there's מנחה Mincha. גדולה, which
is basically from 12:30 to 6:00, and מנחה Mincha קטנה from 3:30
to 6:00. And then he said half of one of those units.
Which half? The first unit, 12:30 to 3:30, or the second unit,
3:30 to 6:00? So he says: תא שמע, Ta Shema, come and
hear. דתניא, Detanya, as it was taught: רבי יהודה אומר פלג מנחה
אחרונה אמרו. Rabbi Yehuda Omer Pelag Mincha Achrona Amru. Half of the
last unit, of the 3:30 to 6:00. So if you divide that
in half, then you have 4:45. Okay, and now, right, 3:30 to
6:00, 4:45. Okay. והיא חד
עשר שעות חסר רביע. Vehi Chad Asar Sha'ot Chasar Revi'a. And that
is eleven hours, which would get you into 5:00 minus a quarter,
4:45. Okay. Now that we have a clear ברייתא Baraita that says
it's all about the קרבנות korbanot, and the time is all about
the קרבנות. korbanot So says the גמרא: Gemara נימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי
יהושע בן לוי. Neyma Tehei Tyuvta DeRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Maybe this
is a contradiction of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
It's very clear all the times are about the קרבנות. korbanot Clearly
that's what it's about. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר לך רבי
יהושע בן לוי, Amar Lach Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, no, he would
say back to you: לעולם אימא לך תפילות אבות תיקנום. Le'olam Eima
Lach Tefillot Avot Tiknum. I'm always going to tell you that it's
basically about the fathers, it's basically about this inner human experience of
prayer. ואסמכינהו רבנן אקרבנות. Ve'asmechinenhu Rabbanan A'korbanot.
We start with the human experience of prayer and then we connect
them onto the קרבנות. korbanot But that is a second layer. דאי
לא תימא הכי, De'i Lo Teima Hachi, because obviously I have to
admit there's a קרבן Korban element. Why do I have to admit
there's a קרבן korban element? תפילת מוסף לרבי יהושע בן לוי מאן
תיקנה? Tefillat Musaf LeRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi Man Tiknah? How do you
explain מוסף? Musaf? מוסף Musaf isn't about אברהם יצחק ויעקב. אלא תפילות
אבות תיקנום. Ela Tefillot Avot Tiknum.
So we're not denying the קרבן korban, element. Everybody agrees that there
is this formal fixed nature of prayer. But I, what I'm saying
is at the core it's about אבות. ואסמכינהו רבנן אקרבנות. Ve'asmechinenhu Rabbanan
A'korbanot. And then the rabbis, after we've established what the core prayer
is, it doesn't start by this external demand, you have to pray
three times a day, here's a text. It starts with the internal
human experience of the need of prayer and then it gets connected
and it gets formalized through the mold of קרבנות. korbanot. And then
you can have מוסף, Musaf, which is all about קרבנות. korbanot. By
the way, because מוסף Musaf is all about קרבנות, korbanot תוספות Tosafot
says and others say, you can't make up מוסף Musaf if you
missed it. Right, the whole reason you can make it up, what
we discussed before when you miss it, is because at the core
it's not just about some external obligation. מוסף, Musaf, which was just
all about קרבנות, korbanot, if you miss it עבר יומו בטל קרבנו,
Avar Yomo Batel Korbano, you can't make it up the next day.
Okay, but this is the double layer. This double layer, by the
way, is also expressed by רמבם Rambam in the context of biblical
and rabbinic. The רמבם Rambam says there's a biblical obligation to pray
every day. That's debated, but that's what רמבם Rambam, says. But he
says that obligation has no fixed time, no fixed word, you know,
you say whatever you want, that's your biblical obligation. The rabbinic obligation
is all of this structure.
But according to this explanation, I don't see the difference between between
the two.
There's a huge difference. One sees it fundamentally starts from the human
experience. So therefore this issue, for example, if I said to you,
is it a good thing or not a good thing to find
places in the prayer to add your own words, right, which is
a question we're going to see that debated later on. So if
you fundamentally think it's about the human experience, we've given it the
form of קרבנות, korbanot. but we would like to give an opportunity
to express that human experience in a more personal way as well,
find that opportunity. If all it is is, "Here's the text, buddy,
you say it," that would be like saying, is it a good
thing or bad thing to add some type of decoration to my
תפילין? tefillin? Okay, right? So you have a fixed text, you do
it, it's not about you, it's about doing the thing that you're
being given to say.
But wouldn't someone use the expression אבות תקנום avot tiknum and when
when we talk about קרבנות korbanot, it says כנגד?
I know. So so it's a little imprecise, but it's I think
very clear, and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi makes it even clearer because the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi says by both כנגד. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi says כנגד אבות
or כנגד קרבנות. korbanot And I think you have to read it
that way. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי יהודה אומר
עד ארבע שעות. Rabbi Yehuda omer ad arba sha'ot. So after that
now we get to some of the back to the הלכתי halachic
discussion, the type of קרבנות korbanot discussion. Okay, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu,
they raise a question. When he says until four hours in the
day for שחרית, Shacharit. עד ועד בכלל ad ve'ad bichlal up to
the fourth up to and including the fourth hour means through until
10 o'clock, או עד ולא עד בכלל o ad velo ad bichlal
until the beginning of the fourth hour which means until until 9
o'clock, right? Because until 9 o'clock then starts the fourth hour
after 9 o'clock. Okay, so תא שמע ta shema come and hear.
רבי יהודה אומר עד פלג המנחה Rabbi Yehuda omer ad pelag hamincha
until the פלג המנחה, pelag hamincha, which we now said means right
the the second half of the second מנחה. Mincha אי אמרת בשלמא
עד ולא עד בכלל ei amarta bishlama ad velo ad bichlal if
you say until that time, היינו דאיכא בין רבי יהודה ורבנן, hainu
de'ika bein Rabbi Yehuda verabanan, that's a difference. The רבנן rabanan say
until nightfall, and he says פלג המנחה pelag hamincha until, you know,
4:45. אלא אי אמרת עד ועד בכלל ela ei amarta ad ve'ad
bichlal but if you say until and including, so if you include
פלג המנחה, pelag hamincha, you're getting till sunset. You're getting till nightfall,
the פלג המנחה's pelag hamincha that last section. So רבי יהודה היינו
רבנן, Rabbi Yehuda hainu rabanan, he's saying the same thing as the
רבנן. rabanan. אלא מאי ela mai says the גמרא Gemara back top
of כז עמוד א. kaf zayin amud alef. What do you want
to say? עד ולא עד בכלל ad velo ad bichlal up to
and not including? אימא סיפא. eima seifa. ושל מוספים כל
היום, veshel musafim kol hayom, מוסף Musaf you can say the whole
day. רבי יהודה אומר עד שבע שעות Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheva
sha'ot until the seven seven hours. Now if it's the beginning of
the seventh hour, that means until noon. If it's the end of
the seventh hour, it means 1:00. So if you say until and
not including, so when he says until the seventh hour, it means
only until noon.
ותניא vetanya and here's a ברייתא beraita we have. היו לפניו שתי
תפילות אחת של מוסף ואחת של מנחה. hayu lefanav shtei tfilot achat
shel Musaf ve'achat shel Mincha. You have two prayers. אחת של מוסף
ואחת של מנחה. achat shel Musaf ve'achat shel Mincha. You're in the
afternoon and you have to דאוון daven מנחה Mincha but you also
haven't דאוונד davened מוסף Musaf yet. מתפלל של מנחה ואחר כך מתפלל
של מוסף. mitpalel shel Mincha ve'achar kach mitpalel shel Musaf. This is
actually the הלכה, halacha, although many people are not aware and when
שולס shuls go over they usually are not מקפיד makpid on this,
but but the הלכה halacha is you דאוון daven מנחה Mincha first
and then מוסף Musaf because מנחה Mincha is תדיר. tadir. שזו תדירה
וזו אינה תדירה. shezo tadira vezo eina tadira. מנחה Mincha is more
common than מוסף. Musaf. So if you're already in the afternoon hours,
מנחה Mincha. comes before מנחה—before Mincha מוסף, Musaf,
thank you, מנחה Mincha, comes before מוסף. Musaf. רבי יהודה אומר מתפלל
של מוסף ואחר כך
של מנחה. Rabbi Yehuda omer mitpalel shel Musaf ve'achar kach shel Mincha.
First מוסף Musaf then מנחה. Mincha. Why? שזו עוברת וזו אינה עוברת.
shezo overet vezo eina overet. Since I say that מוסף Musaf can
be only דאוונד davened until the seventh hour, then you've got to—you
know, you're on the clock. You know, you're on the—that's the wrong
phrase. But anyway, you know, the clock is ticking. So you've got
to דאוון daven מוסף Musaf first or you're going to lose the
opportunity. So first דאוון daven מוסף Musaf and then מנחה. Mincha. One
is the time is passing, the other is not. So אי אמרת
בשלמא עד ועד בכלל ei amarta bishlama ad ve'ad bichlal if you
say until means until and including, היינו דמשכחת להו שתי תפילות בהדי
הדדי, hainu demishkachat lehu shtei tfilot bahadi hadadi, then I can get
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda a time where it's both מנחה
mincha and מוסף Musaf time, which is between 12 and 1:00. Actually
between 12:30 and 1:00 because you really can't דאוון daven מנחה mincha?
before 12:30. By the way, all the times I'm giving are זמניות.
zmaniyot. I was going to say that. All the times I'm giving,
I'm giving in a perfect day assuming sunrise is at six, sunset
is at six, each hour is an hour. But basically you have
to adjust it for—it's all hours from sunrise and the length of
the hours are based on dividing the daytime hours into 12. Okay,
12 equal parts. So I'm just giving these times for simplicity, but
it's adjusted for שעות זמניות. sha'ot zmaniyot. So if רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says that you can דאוון daven מוסף Musaf until one, then
we have a time where מוסף Musaf and מנחה mincha overlap between
12:30 and one.
אלא—so ela then we get it. אלא אי אמרת עד ולא עד
בכלל. ela ei amarta ad velo ad bichlal. But if he says
until the beginning of the seventh hour, until 12 o'clock, היכי משכחת
להו שתי תפילות בהדי הדדי? heichi mishkachat lehu shtei tfilot bahadi hadadi?
You're never going to get מנחה mincha and מוסף Musaf two דאוונינגס
davenings at the same time.
כי כיוון דאתא ליה זמן מנחה ki keivan de'ata leh zman Mincha
when מנחה mincha time comes, אזל ליה זמן מוסף, azal leh zman
Musaf, מוסף Musaf time has passed. So you see that when he
says until, he means until and including. So the גמרא Gemara says
fine. אלא מאי עד ועד בכלל ela mai ad ve'ad bichlal so
you want to say including? So means including the seventh hour, מוסף
Musaf is until 1:00. So קשיא רישא. kashya reisha. How about when
we said until Till פלג המנחה. Plag HaMincha. If you say including,
it's going to get you to nightfall. So מאי איכא בין רבי
יהודה לרבנן, mai ika bein Rabbi Yehuda l'Rabbanan, what's their difference if
including פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha gets you till nightfall? So the גמרא
Gemara. says no. מי סברת דהאי פלג המנחה mi savrat dehai Plag
HaMincha when he says until and now we say it means until
and including פלג המנחה? Plag HaMincha? פלג Plag means half by the
way. Who tells you that the half מנחה mincha is פלג אחרונה,
Plag achrona, the second half? קאמר ka'amar
פלג ראשונה קאמר, Plag rishona ka'amar, he's saying the first half. Right,
if you look at the time from 3:30 to 6:00 and you
divide it in half and you have two פלג המנחהs, Plag HaMinchas,
two halves. You have the first half from 3:30 to 4:45 and
the second half from 4:45 to 6:00. So when he says until
פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha and now we say until and including, it
means until and including the first half of מנחה. mincha So it's
through the 3:30 to 4:45 time, which gets you to the beginning
of the second half of פלג המנחה. Plag HaMincha. והכי קאמר, v'hachi
ka'amar, where were we? והכי קאמר, v'hachi ka'amar, this is what he's
saying: אימת נפיק פלג ראשונה ועייל פלג אחרונה, eimat nafik Plag rishona
v'ayeil Plag achrona, when does the first פלג Plag end, the first
half of this second period end, and the second half begin? מכי
נפיק י"א שעות חסר רביע michei nafik achas esrei sha'os chasar revia
when it's past 10:45. And that's when you can דאוון. daven. So
now we have determined that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says עד ועד
בכלל, ad v'ad bichlal, so פלג המנחה Plag HaMincha we know is
until 4:45 and מוסף Musaf according to him is until 1 o'clock.
We don't פסק pasken like him for מוסף. Musaf. We'll see how
we פסק. pasken. מוסף Musaf we פסק pasken the whole day. We'll
see how we פסק pasken by מנחה mincha in a little bit.
So the גמרא Gemara says תנינא, tanina, we taught in a ברייתא...
Braita... oh I'm sorry, excuse me. אמר רב נחמן... Amar Rav Nachman...
okay, אמר רב נחמן. Amar Rav Nachman. Before we go on though,
I do want to say something that ties this back though to
the קרבן korban, discussion is the following: is that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is the most clear that really pushes the קרבן, korban right?
Because he very much says you can only say until this time,
this is the קרבן, korban this is when this קרבן korban? was
brought, this is when that קרבן korban was brought, and so on.
You also see it by the way that he insists that מוסף
Musaf precedes מנחה, mincha although he explains it based on one has
a passing time and the other doesn't have a passing time, the
result is we're keeping the structure of קרבנות korbanot, that מוסף Musaf
always comes before מנחה. mincha Okay, it also might be, you know,
Michael asked before about the whole debate about like, well, when did
they really bring the קרבן? korban Did they bring it the whole
day or did they bring it until פלג המנחה? Plag HaMincha? Well,
I think we can all agree that probably in practice they brought
it till פלג המנחה. Plag HaMincha. The question was in theory how
long you could say, but how long you could bring it. But
if you're saying the whole morning, the whole afternoon, you might clearly,
you know, you might say that in theory that connects to times
of קרבנות. But at the, but you know, it certainly is much
more corresponds to this other model of דאוונינג davening different times of
the day, and it's not about קרבנות. You know, it's שחרית מנחה
ומעריב, Shacharit, Mincha, u'Ma'ariv, and that's what the ירושלמי says by the
way, that a way to understand morning, afternoon, and evening is nothing
to do with קרבנות but has to do with the human experience
at different times during the day. So the רבנן Rabbanan that argue
on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could be seen as arguing details of
קרבנות, but could be really seen as much more in the sort
of human experience camp and not in the קרבן korban camp. Okay,
and now let's take a look at how we פסק pasken about
this. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so it said רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tanina, we taught similarly in
a משנה. Mishnah. רבי יהודה בן בבא העיד חמישה דברים, Rabbi Yehuda
ben Bava he'id chamisha devarim, this is in עדיות Eduyot where people
are giving testimony about past teachings and about things that they had
heard in the past, which is when they were just formulating, you
know, post-חורבן post-Churban the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in יבנה. Yavne. So רבי יהודה
בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava testified five things that he had
heard from previous teachers that got entered into the record here. One
is שממאנים את הקטנה, she'm'ma'anim et ha'ketana, that they would have a
rabbinic institution that you could, the mother and the brother if there
was no father could marry off the underage daughter, which was a
societal economic need at the time to ensure that she was going
to be taken care of for. And there would be times where
it would be important—now she had the right to refuse the wedding
anytime, the marriage anytime before she became an adult, 12 years old,
which is a halachic adult. So normally we would let it be
her choice, but there would be times where we would actually encourage
her to be ממאן, mema'en, to refuse the wedding, because it would
get in the way of other halachic considerations, like if there was
a case of ייבום, yibum, the fact that she had a marriage
to this guy was not a halachic marriage could create certain ייבום
yibum problems. I don't want to go into
details, and therefore it could be we would encourage her to do
מיאון. miun. So that was one thing he taught, that there will
be times that we would be ממאן, mema'en, we would teach her
to do מיאון. miun. Number two: שמשיאין את האשה על פי עד
אחד, she'mashi'in et ha'isha al pi ed echad,
that this is a very important הלכה halacha that a whole פרק
perek in יבמות, Yevamot, that if a woman's husband is missing and
we don't know what the story is, that we accept even one
person's testimony. We sort of waive most of the laws of testimony—doesn't
matter man or woman, two or one, doesn't matter direct testimony, indirect
testimony—we allow women to remarry. That's number two. Number three: ועל תרנגול
שנסקל בירושלים, v'al tarnigol she'niskal b'Yerushalayim,
there was a chicken that basically killed an infant in ירושלים Yerushalayim
by pecking at its soft spot of the head, and they stoned
it because this is basically the הלכה halacha that a שור הנסקל...
shor ha'niskal... It doesn't have to be an ox. When you stone
an animal for killing somebody, even if it's not an ox, even
if it's a chicken, and he testified that that happened
once, ועל הריגת הנפש, ve-al harigat ha-nefesh, because it killed somebody. A
rooster, thank you. I guess roosters tend to be a little bit
more violent than chickens, right? What? It says a rooster, that's right.
It's תרנגול, tarnegol, not תרנגולת, tarnegolet, that's right. Isn't chicken gender neutral?
No? But true, chicken I think you think about a hen. That's
true. Okay, anyway, roosters tend to be right, roosters can be a
little violent.
I'm not a מומחה, mumche, I just mean the word.
Right, you're right. Okay, thank you. All right, a rooster that killed
an infant in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ועל יין בן ארבעים יום שנתנסך על גבי המזבח, ve-al
yayin ben arba’im yom she-nitnasech al gabi ha-mizbe’ach, wine, when does something
become wine instead of being grape juice? Because you only could use
wine on the altar. So he says even once it was 40
days old, it had enough to at least start the fermentation
process, so although obviously it wasn't wine yet, it wasn't considered סתם
stam grape juice and they could use it to do wine libations
on the altar, which gets into interesting questions about our using of
grape juice for קידוש, Kiddush, which I'm not going to discuss now.
ועל תמיד של שחר ve-al tamid shel shachar and here's the part
that's relevant to us, number five,
the morning sacrifice שקרב בארבע שעות she-karav be-arba sha’ot that was brought
at the fourth hour. Now again, does that mean that it was
always brought by the fourth hour? Does it mean it was אסור
asur to bring it afterwards? But anyway, the relevance for us is
that שמע מינה עד ועד בכלל, shma mina ad ve-ad bichlal, it's
inclusive. Why? Because it doesn't say עד ארבע שעות, ad arba sha’ot,
but it says בארבע שעות, be-arba sha’ot, in the fourth hour. So
you see that once, yeah, that's the only distinction we're making, so
you see when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says fourth hour he means
including the fourth hour, because that's corresponding to this testimony. אמר רב
כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, now here becomes a very important הלכה, halakha,
הלכה כרבי יהודה, halakha ke-Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda by שחרית, Shacharit הואיל ותנן בבחירתא כוותיה, ho’il ve-tnan be-vchirata kevataih,
because we taught in the choice ones like him. What does it
mean the choice ones? עדיות Eduyot is called בחירתא bechirata because it
is the מסכתא masechta which has you know, very selective things that
are being testified and comes from like very early sources. So anything,
the general rule is things that were testified to in מסכת עדיות,
Masechet Eduyot, which is one of the earliest מסכתות, masechtot, we assume
that we actually, generally the assumption is we rule that way. Now
the interesting thing is though that this teaching in עדיות Eduyot did
not say till when can you דאוון daven מנחה. mincha The teaching
in עדיות Eduyot just said till when was the קרבן korban brought.
So first of all, the question I think is a little, did
it say that it was you know, just if in practice it
was always brought in the fourth hour, does that say that if
they had missed it, they wouldn't have brought it later? That's not
clear. But let's even assume that, that they would not have brought
it later, that that was part of the testimony. It doesn't prove
that דאוונינג davening can only be until the fourth hour. That's only
if you assume that דאוונינג davening is linked strongly to קרבנות. So
by the גמרא Gemara basing this as saying we rule like רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, it's also ruling the קרבן korban aspect. But again,
remember as we said at the bottom of the previous דף, daf,
right, nobody denies the קרבן korban aspect, there is a fixed nature
to דאוונינג, davening, there is a sense of times, there is a
sense of texts. Okay, so everybody has to concede to that to
a certain degree. So now what we have is because the קרבן
korban is brought until 10 o'clock and because at some level the
דאוונינגס davenings are linked to the קרבנות, you can only דאוון שחרית
daven Shacharit till 10 o'clock and that's actually what we say, at
least that the core, your יוצא תפילה, yotzei tefillah, the זמן תפילה
zman tefillah ends at the end of four hours in the day.
If you miss that, you can דאוון daven afterwards but it's considered
your דאוונינג davening is שלא בזמנה. she-lo bi-zmanah. But the real זמן,
zman, so there still remains a certain degree of latitude there but
the real, I mean, or not absolute I should say, but we
basically do rule that the זמן תפילה zman tefillah is until four
hours of the day.
That means until חצות, Chatzot, right, that you're allowed to דאוון. daven.
Well, it's not תפילה בזמנה, tefillah bi-zmanah, but it still counts as
תפילה until חצות, Chatzot, שחרית. Shacharit Okay, so now let's take a
look at the גמרא.
Gemara Who was רב יהודה? Rav Yehuda?
He was a student of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so he was
I guess a mid to late second century.
Okay, all
right, so
yeah,
second century, I'm sorry, second century. 100, I meant second, I was
thinking 100 because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was like 130, right, mid
to late second century.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was...
Did you say שחרית Shacharit until חצות? Chatzot? What? Did you say
שחרית Shacharit until?
No, שחרית Shacharit, is right, right, I'm sorry, I just was thinking
130, 135 and I said first, I meant second. Anyway, no, שחרית
Shacharit. we rule like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that שחרית, Shacharit the
זמן שחרית zman Shacharit is until 10 o'clock on a perfect day.
But if you miss 10 o'clock, you can still דאוון שמונה עשרה
daven Shemoneh Esrei but it counts as תפילה שלא בזמנה. tefillah she-lo
bi-zmanah. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues, ועל תמיד של שחר שקרב בארבע שעות. ve-al tamid
shel shachar she-karav be-arba sha’ot. So now we've already sort of ruled
that way, but now we're looking at the line in the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so מאן תנא להא דתנן, man tanna le-ha de-tnan, who
taught what we taught in the משנה? Mishnah? החמה שמשתבת ומסא, ha-chamah
she-meshatevet u-mesa, actually it's not a משנה, Mishnah, it's a מכילתא Mekhilta
whatever, but anyway, that the sun heated and the מן man melted.
בארבע שעות, be-arba sha’ot, that happened at the fourth hour in the
day, 10 o'clock.
את אומר בארבע שעות או אינו אלא בשש שעות, at omer be-arba
sha’ot o eino ela be-shesh sha’ot, you say it's at the fourth
hour, maybe it's at noon time, that's when the sun. is really
hot.
כשהוא אומר keshu omer when the verse says כחום היום ke'chom ha'yom
like the heat of the day, so the heat of the day,
that is הרי שש שעות harei shesh sha'ot and more. The heat
is the hottest part, that's at noon.
הא מני מקיים ha mani mekayem actually, you know, sometimes not true,
it's hotter later in the day because the air is heating up
throughout the day. But anyway, but okay, the sun beats down most
directly on you at noon. הא מני מקיים ha mani mekayem וחם
השמש ונמס? ve'cham ha'shemesh ve'namas? So what does it mean the sun
heated, which means it began to heat, it doesn't mean it's the
hottest part of the day? So that is בארבע שעות, be'arba sha'ot,
that's at four hours, 10 o'clock. So who says that? מני, mani,
who is that? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבנן. lo Rabbi Yehuda ve'lo
Rabbanan. So somehow we're going to connect this to the debate of
Rabbi Yehuda and the Rabbis. אי רבי יהודה, ei Rabbi Yehuda, if
it's Rabbi Yehuda, עד ארבע שעות נמי צפרא הוא. ad arba sha'ot
nami tsafra hu. So he wouldn't say, right, so the point is
that the Torah says that they gathered the manna when? בבקר, be'voker,
in the morning. So according to him, right, so, so בבקר be'voker
is until, includes the 10 o'clock, until 10 o'clock. So it would
not be the period, the sun didn't, the manna only melted after
בבקר. be'voker. They gathered the manna in the בבקר. be'voker. So according
to him, right, why do we say, why do we say it
melted in the fourth hour? That's still בבקר be'voker for him. ואי
רבנן, ve'ei Rabbanan, if it's according to the Rabbis, עד חצות נמי
צפרא הוא. ad chatsot nami tsafra hu. It's until חצות chatsot it's
considered בבקר. be'voker. So why would the manna have melted? So the
Gemara says, אי בעית אימא רבי יהודה אי בעית אימא רבנן. ei
ba'it eima Rabbi Yehuda ei ba'it eima Rabbanan. I could make it
work either way. אי בעית אימא רבנן, ei ba'it eima Rabbanan, אמר
קרא amar kra בבקר בבקר, be'voker be'voker, in the morning, in the
morning.
חלקיהו לשני בקרים. chalkeyhu l'shnei bekarim. Now, divide it into two, to
the first half of the morning and the second half. At the
פלג בקר, plag voker, exactly. Now, we are assuming by the way,
when it says that it melted in the fourth hour, it means,
which explains what the question was, the beginning of the fourth hour.
It means at 9 o'clock. Okay, I think I misstated that before.
So now we're saying, why would it have melted according to Rabbi
Yehuda at the beginning of the fourth hour, 9 o'clock? It's still
בבקר be'voker until 10 o'clock. So it says, it says בבקר בבקר,
be'voker be'voker, divide it into two. So for the Rabbis, that means
the first half of the morning is till nine, the second half
is from nine to twelve. So they collected it till nine and
it melted in the second half of the morning. Okay, so where
were we? So that's the Rabbis. You have, so their whole בבקר
be'voker is till twelve. You divide the בבקר be'voker into two halves
and it melts at the beginning of the fourth hour, it melts
at the end of the first half, 9 o'clock. ואי בעית אימא
רבי יהודה, ve'ei ba'it eima Rabbi Yehuda, if you want Rabbi Yehuda,
האי בקר יתירא, hai voker yateira, we're not splitting the בבקר, be'voker,
but it has an extra בבקר be'voker להקדים לו שעה אחת, le'hakdim
lo sha'ah achat, to say only early in the morning. בבקר be'voker
goes till, it's true 10 o'clock according to him, but בבקר בבקר
be'voker be'voker tells me do it earlier in the morning. So they
collect the manna at the earlier part of the morning till nine,
and the last hour of בבקר, be'voker, right, at 9 o'clock, then
it would already start melting even though it was still בבקר. be'voker.
Still a different paradigm, in other
words, I know I'm going to say that, I know, hold on,
I'm going to say that. Okay, so the Gemara says, דכולי עלמא
מיהא וחם השמש ונמס בארבע שעות. de'kulei alma miha ve'cham ha'shemesh ve'namas
be'arba sha'ot. But everybody agrees וחם השמש ונמס ve'cham ha'shemesh ve'namas means
at the beginning of the fourth hour, at 9 o'clock. מאי משמע,
mai mashma, where do you get that from? אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב אמר קרא amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar kra וחם השמש
ונמס, ve'cham ha'shemesh ve'namas, it heated and it melted. איזו היא שעה
שהשמש חם והצל צונן, eizu hi sha'ah she'ha'shemesh cham ve'ha'tsel tsonen, the
sun is
hot, but in the shaded area it's still cool? It's not like
the other פסוק pasuk כחום היום, ke'chom ha'yom, the whole day is
hot, every place is hot. Here it's just in the sun it's
hot. So what time is that? הוי אומר בארבע שעות, hevei omer
be'arba sha'ot, starting at 9 o'clock it's hot if you're in the
sun, it's not hot if you're in shade. Now, as Dov correctly
said, what does this have to do with Rabbi Yehuda or the
Rabbis? They're debating when you can bring the morning sacrifice. So the
fact that the Gemara makes it dependent on it says that to
some degree, maybe we can say they're debating not the morning sacrifice
but what's considered בבקר. be'voker. And the Rabbis say בבקר be'voker is
the whole morning, Rabbi Yehuda says בבקר be'voker is until 10 o'clock,
which by the way could be explained completely not related to sacrifices
and completely based on the human experience of prayer. There's a different
prayer of the morning hours as when daybreak, בבקר be'voker is really
daybreak, right? So therefore, there's a certain type of a experience of
the need to relate to God and to experience the beauty of
nature at בבקר, be'voker, at daybreak, is very different than at 11
o'clock in the morning. Okay, so the Gemara is saying maybe they're,
you know, this Gemara is really I think in contrast to the
previous one because what does קרבנות have to do with whether you
call it בבקר, be'voker, unless you say, you know, the תמיד tamid
and it says, you know, you bring the תמיד בבקר בבקר, tamid
be'voker be'voker, maybe that's true and maybe they're indirectly connecting it. But
it would have been nice if they would have spelled that out,
but that could be. It could still be getting to the קרבן
through the בבקר be'voker of the תמיד. tamid. But it could also
be a basic question of what does תפילת בבקר tefillat be'voker mean,
not just תפילת שחרית, tefillat shacharit, but תפילת בבקר tefillat be'voker and
what, first part of the morning or the whole morning.
We also pray according to this paradigm
כנגד המן. keneged ha'man. Right, we're praying to הקדוש ברוך הוא. ha'Kadosh
Baruch Hu. Give us food.
Oh, that's a beautiful point too, right?
Yeah, another, another feeling here of, of once there's a basic paradigm
between קרבנות and the אבות, yeah, it's like the Gemara now feels
the freedom to, to suggest to explore any number of...
Oh, that's a nice way of thinking about it too. So we're
not just sort of still arguing which one. Okay, we accept קרבנות,
we accept the fixed nature, but let's sort of give still expression
to... Right in a way sort of saying but we have this
base of אבות, let's still find ways to take that, to take
those structures and bring the אבות aspect to it. I like this,
it's very beautiful. And the idea of the מן man also is
very nice. So let's just let's try to get a little bit
further here to get to הלכה. halacha. זמן תפילת המנחה עד הערב.
Zman tfilat hamincha ad ha'erev. So מנחה is until night. So and
here רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says until four and three quarters. So
אמר ליה רב חסדא לרבי יצחק. Amar lei Rav Chisda l'Rabbi Yitzchak.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, התם
hatam אמרת הלכה כרבי יהודה, amart halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, we just finished
ruling like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by four hours for שחרית. הוא
דתנן בבחירתא כוותיה, Hu detnan b'bechirta kvatei, since we taught it עדיות
Eduyos like him. So you can only say שחרית at least בזמנו
bizmano until 10:00. הכא מאי? Hacha mai? What about here by מנחה?
Is it till 4:45 or the whole afternoon? אישתיק ולא אמר ליה
מידי. Ishtik v'lo amar lei midi. He didn't know. He's quieted. אמר
רב חסדא נחזי אנן. Amar Rav Chisda nachzei anan. So said רב
חסדא, Rav Chisda, okay let's let's try to figure it out.
מדרב מצלי של שבת בערב שבת מבעוד יום, Mi-deRav matzli shel Shabbat
b'erev Shabbat mi-be'od yom, רב Rav. davened a מעריב Ma'ariv for שבת
Shabbat before before sunset. Right? Davened an early שבת, Shabbat, an early
שבת. Shabbat. שמע מינה הלכה כרבי יהודה. Shema mina halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda.
You see he rules like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because presumably if
מנחה time ends at 4:45, מעריב Ma'ariv time begins at 4:45. So
if somebody davened מעריב Ma'ariv before sunset, he's ruling like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda.
It could be in a different liturgical day.
Yes, exactly, exactly.
So the גמרא says אדרבה, aderaba, the opposite, מדרב הונא ורבנן לא
הוו מצלי עד אורתא, mi-deRav Huna v'rabanan lo havu matzli ad orta,
רב הונא Rav Huna and the רבנן rabanan wouldn't daven an early
שבת Shabbat even though maybe they were there was a need to.
שמע מינה אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. Shema mina ein halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda.
They didn't rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא says
השתא דלא איתמר הלכתא לא כמר ולא כמר, Hashta d'lo itmar hilchata
lo kemar v'lo kemar, since we don't have a clear ruling like
either position, דעבד כמר עבד ודעבד כמר עבד, de-avad kemar avad u-de-avad
kemar avad, you want you can go like this one, you want
you can go like that one. Now okay
so so first of all two things. The גמרא makes it dependent
that מנחה and מעריב Ma'ariv are dependent. It's interesting to note are
what? מנחה and מעריב Ma'ariv are dependent on both on both this
debate. Although it should be noted that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda himself
never ruled that מעריב Ma'ariv starts after פלג המנחה. Plag Hamincha. I
mean that was never clear. If you look at the רמב"ם, Rambam
the רמב"ם says okay you should try to daven מנחה before פלג
המנחה Plag Hamincha but if you miss פלג המנחה Plag Hamincha you
could daven it until sunset. He never says you can daven מעריב
Ma'ariv by פלג המנחה. Plag Hamincha. He does say by ערב שבת.
erev Shabbat. That's a different and he sort of says by ערב
שבת erev Shabbat you can because מנחה is—מעריב Ma'ariv is רשות. reshut.
He sort of like makes it a special case. He doesn't directly
make it dependent on this. The general assumption though is that both
things are being debated. So when can you daven מנחה and when
can you start מעריב? Ma'ariv? And then the question what does it
mean דעבד כמר? de-avad kemar? Does it mean I have to be
consistent throughout my life? And the general answer seems to be no.
It means like you can choose, you know, maybe today rely on
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the other day the רבנן. rabanan. The real
and again it has an implication when you start to stop מנחה
and when you start מעריב. Ma'ariv. The big problem is is when
you try to do both in a contradictory way.
When you mix them which שול shul does.
Not only this שול, shul, almost every single שול. shul. When they
make an early שבת, Shabbat, you know they will daven during the
week they know they situate מעריב Ma'ariv so it's before and after
שקיעה, shkiya, maybe sometimes before and after פלג. Plag. But when they
make early שבת Shabbat they very often daven both מנחה and מעריב,
Ma'ariv, you know, either both before—well before פלג Plag they'd have a
huge issue because for being מקבל שבת mekabel Shabbat or whatever. But
they'll often daven places will daven both מנחה and מעריב Ma'ariv after
פלג. Plag. Okay and that is a real problem. Can you be
that contradictory? Okay but that is and again same פלג Plag starts
מעריב Ma'ariv we should note does not work with the קרבן paradigm.
No right I mean unless you wanted to argue that since at
night they were burning the fats and that started in the prior
previous day. Right you could you could say that but it should
be noted that none of this is being said okay? So and
but we do somehow assume that פלג המנחה Plag Hamincha becomes for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda a time to begin מעריב Ma'ariv and you
know though it's a liturgical time we will see also that has
relevance for other הלכות. halachot. How much can פלג המנחה Plag Hamincha
be related to the next day? So like when you make an
early שבת Shabbat you can't make it prior to פלג המנחה. Plag
Hamincha. So now we're introducing a concept that פלג המנחה Plag Hamincha
becomes like connected to the to the following day. And let's just
read I know we're a little over let's just read just one
more one more line and then we'll wrap up for now. It
says like this
okay דעבד כמר עבד. de-avad kemar avad. רב איקלע לבי גניבא, Rav
ikla l'vei Gneiva, רב Rav came to גניבא's Gneiva house וצלי של
שבת בערב שבת v'tzali shel Shabbat b'erev Shabbat and he was davening
שבת Shabbat davening מעריב Ma'ariv when it was still before sunset. והוה
מצלי רבי ירמיה בר אבא לאחוריה, V'hava matzli Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba
l'achorei, רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba was davening behind
it behind רב. Rav וסיים רב, V'siyem Rav, רב finished his שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esreh ולא פסקיה לצלותיה דרבי ירמיה v'lo paskei l'tzlutei d'Rabbi
Yirmiyah and he didn't interrupt the davening he didn't walk in front
of רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiyah, he didn't take three steps back where
he'd be moving into his space or he didn't walk in front
of him to get to his seat. שמע מינה תלת Shema mina
tlat and you can see from this three things. שמע מינה מתפלל
אדם של שבת בערב שבת, Shema mina mitpalel adam shel Shabbat b'erev
Shabbat, a רב was davening שבת Shabbat when it was still Friday
so מעריב Ma'ariv he was making an early שבת Shabbat you can
do that before sunset.
ושמע מינה מתפלל תלמיד אחורי רבו, V'shema mina mitpalel talmid achorei rabbo,
a תלמיד talmid can daven behind his רבי, Rebbi, it's not considered
as not respectful it's not considered like he's bowing down to his
רבי Rebbi as opposed to on the
side okay. ושמע מינה אסור לעבור כנגד המתפללים, V'shema mina assur la'avor
k'neged hamitpalelim, you can't walk in front of people that are davening.
מסייע ליה לרבי יהושע בן לוי, Mesayei lei l'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
it supports רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, דאמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי, D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, אסור לעבור כנגד המתפללים,
Assur la'avor keneged hamispallelim, you cannot walk in front of people that
are דאווענינג. davening. The גמרא says איני, eini, is that true? Because
you're interrupting their דאווענינג, davening, distracting them. והא רבי אמי ורבי אסי
חלפי, V'ha Rabbi Ammi v'Rabbi Assi chalfei, didn't רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi
and רבי אסי Rabbi Assi walk in front of people when they
were דאווענינג? davening? And רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi and רבי אסי Rabbi
Assi חוץ לארבע אמות הוא דחלפי. chutz l'arba amos hu d'chalfei. רבי
אמי Rabbi Ammi and
רבי אסי Rabbi Assi would walk outside of their four אמות. amos.
Within their four אמות, amos, you cannot walk in front of them.
People violate this all the time. It really, besides being a הלכה,
Halacha, can be very distracting to people that are דאווענינג, davening, and
something people really have to work on being מקפיד makpid about. And
we will continue with this tomorrow.